Guide to the Harold Wickliffe Rose Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Harold Wickliffe Rose papers
1924-1972
MS 1239
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.75
The papers consist entirely of materials relating to Rose's book, The Colonial Houses of Worship in America (1963). Included are the manuscript, related correspondence, reviews, and a large amount of research material: notes, letters, and printed and pictorial matter about churches in eighteen states. Among his correspondents are Frederick W. Beinecke, A. Pierce Middleton, Richmond P. Miller and Edmund W. Sinnott.
Rose, H. Wickliffe (Harold Wickliffe), 1896-1970
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Yale University Art and Architecture Library, 1980.
Scope and Contents
The Harold Wickliffe Rose Papers consist entirely of materials relating to his book, The Colonial Houses of Worship in America (1963). Besides the actual manuscript, the collection includes correspondence during and after the writing of the book, printed reviews, and a large amount of research material: notes, letters of inquiry, and printed and pictorial matter about churches.
The most valuable material in the papers is the collection of original photographs of churches. As the book's subtitle explains, Rose attempted to record every American church "built in the English colonies before the Republic, 1607 – 1789, and still standing." He was not completely successful, but he did take more than 400 photographs of churches in eighteen states. Most of these photographs—some of which were not published in the book—are arranged by state in boxes 5-12; in many cases there are a 4 by 5" negative, a 4 by 5" print, and an 8 by 10" print of each photograph. There are also large mounted photographs in the two folio boxes, and some photographs in the correspondence folders.
In the research material, boxes 5-12, the notes, correspondence and printed matter for each state are arranged chronologically, while the photographs, in separate folders, are arranged alphabetically by the name of town or county, with less clearly indentified photographs at the end. There are separate folders, containing both notes and photographs, for particularly well-documented churches.
The papers were given by Mrs. Elizabeth Rose to the Yale Art and Architecture Library, and transferred to Manuscripts and Archives in October 1980.
Biographical / Historical
Harold Wickliffe Rose: A.B., Harvard, 1919; worked for American Viscose Corp. as southern sales manager; in New York City, 1924; in Charlotte, N.C., 1925-1932; as sales manager, rayon staple, 1935-1942; coordinator of research and planning at main office, Wilmington, Del., 1942-1946; general assistant to president at main office, Philadelphia, 1946-1953; president, director, and general manager, Linen Thread Co., 1953-1957 and Dolphin Jute Mills, 1956-1957; author of The Colonial Houses of Worship in America.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Architecture; Church Buildings -- United States; Religion; Photographic prints; Beinecke, Frederick W.; Middleton, Arthur Pierce; Miller, Richmond P. (Richmond Pearson), 1902-1972; Rose, H. Wickliffe (Harold Wickliffe), 1896-1970; Sinnott, Edmund W. (Edmund Ware), 1888-1958
- Inventory
  - The Colonial Houses of Worship in America: manuscript, with related drafts and printed matter, 1950-1952, 1960-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 7)
  - Correspondence with publisher, Hastings House, 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 8 - 9)
  - Correspondence with publisher, Hastings House, 1964-1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Corrspondence with editor, Katie Cardinal, 1960-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence with other publishers, 1945-1958, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence
    - Beinecke, Frederick W., 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Middleton, A. Pierce, 1960-1962, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Miller, Richmond P., 1950-1958 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Sinnott, Edmund W., 1963-1965 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - U.S. Department of the Interior: National Survery of Historic Sites and Buildings, 1962-1963, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous, 1938, 1950-1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 18 - 20)
  - Correspondence and notes re: photographs, 1960-1963, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence re: reproduction of Rose's photographs, 1941, 1965-1972 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence and notes re: errata and omissions, 1963-1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence and notes re: distrubution, review copies, 1963-1964, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Reviews and related correspondence, 1963-1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 25 - 26)
  - Royalty statements and other financial papers, 1960-1966, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Address book, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Notes, 1935-1953, undated (Box 3, Folder 29 - 30)
  - Notes, 1934-1952, 1961-1963, undated (Box 4, Folder 31 - 36)
  - Printed matter
    - Maps, 1931-1959, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Journals, pamphlets, 1924-1946 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Journals, pamphlets, 1947-1970 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Miscellaneous, 1935-1965, undated (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Research material
    - Connecticut, 1934-1961, undated (Box 5, Folder 41 - 42)
    - Delaware, 1940-1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Delaware, 1936-1952, undated (Box 6, Folder 44)
    - Georgia, 1940-1961, undated (Box 6, Folder 45 - 46)
    - Maine, 1934-1962, undated (Box 6, Folder 47 - 48)
    - Maryland, 1934-1962, undated (Box 6, Folder 49 - 52)
      - Otterbein United Brethren Church, Baltimore, 1947, 1961, undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
      - Trinity Church, Church Creek, 1940, 1960-1961, undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
    - Massachusetts, 1930-1968, undated (Box 7, Folder 55 - 58)
      - Second Congregational Church, North Beverly, 1940-1962 (Box 7, Folder 59)
      - First Baptist Church, Westwood, 1940-1961, undated (Box 7, Folder 60)
    - New Hampshire, 1939-1963, undated (Box 7, Folder 61 - 62)
    - New Hampshire, 1939-1962, undated (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - New Jersey, 1935-1963, undated (Box 8, Folder 64 - 67)
      - St. Thomas' Church, Alexandria, 1959, 1962, undated (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - New York, 1935-1951 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - New York, 1935-1968, undated (Box 9, Folder 70 - 72)
      - Shaker Meeting House, New Lebanon, 1941-1963, undated (Box 9, Folder 73)
      - Schoharie County, 1933-1962, undated (Box 9, Folder 74)
      - Old Fort Niagara, Youngstown, 1961, undated (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - North Carolina, 1939-1962, undated (Box 9, Folder 76 - 77)
    - Pennsylvania, 1939-1950 (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - Pennsylvania, 1941-1963, undated (Box 10, Folder 79 - 85)
    - Pennsylvania, 1945-1952, undated (Box 11, Folder 86)
    - Rhode Island, 1940-1962, undated (Box 11, Folder 87 - 88)
    - South Carolina, 1938-1966, undated (Box 11, Folder 89 - 91)
    - Vermont, 1937-1964, undated (Box 11, Folder 92 - 93)
    - Virginia, 1936-1952 (Box 11, Folder 94 - 95)
    - Virginia, 1936-1965, undated (Box 12, Folder 96 - 101)
      - St. Peter's Church, New Kent County, 1936-1961, undated (Box 12, Folder 102)
      - Williamsburg, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 103)
    - West Virginia, 1947, 1960-1961, undated (Box 12, Folder 104 - 105)
  - Notes and mounted photographs for lecture, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 106)
  - Photographs for book jacket, 1963 (Box 13, Folder 107)
  - Mescellaneous photographs and postcards, 1940, 1941, undated (Box 13, Folder 108)
  - Certificate from Old North Church, Boston, Massachusetts, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 109)
  - Book jackets, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 110)
  - Negatives: Rehoboth Church, West Virginia; Williamsburg, Virginia; Jesuit Chapel, Trinity Church, and various individuals, Maryland, 1947, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 111)
  - Oversize photographs
    - California, Connecticut, Delaware, Louisiana, Maine, Maryland, Massachusetts, New Jersey, New York, Pennsylvania, Rhode Island, undated (Box 14, Folder 112)
    - South Carolina, Virginia, undated (Box 15, Folder 113)